In this section you will hear two long conversations.
At the end of each conversation you will hear four questions.
Both the conversation and the questions will be spoken only once.
After you hear a question, you must choose the best answer from the four choices
marked A, B, C, Then mark the corresponding letter on answer sheet 1 with a single
line through the centre.
Excuse me, where's your rock music section?
Rock music? I'm sorry, we're a jazz store.
We don't have any rock and roll.
Oh, you only have jazz music?
Nothing else? That's right.
We're the only record store in London dedicated exclusively to jazz.
Actually, we're more than just a record store.
We have a and library upstairs, and a ticket office down the hall where you can buy
tickets to all the major jazz concerts in the city.
Also, we have our own studio next door where we produce albums for up -coming
artists. We're committed to fostering new music talent.
Wow, that's so cool.
I guess there's not much of a jazz scene anymore, not like there used to be.
But here you're trying to promote this great music genre.
Yes, indeed. Nowadays, most people like to listen to pop and rock music.
Hip music from America is also getting more and more popular.
So as a result, are fewer listeners of jazz, which is a great shame because it's an
incredibly rich genre.
But that's not to say there isn't any good new jazz music being made out there
anymore. Far from it.
It's just a much smaller market today.
So how would you define jazz?
Well, interestingly enough, there's no agreed -upon definition of jazz.
Indeed, there are many different styles of jazz.
Some have singing, but most don't.
Some are electric, and some aren't.
Some contain live experimentation, but not always.
While there's no simple definition for it, and while there are many different styles
of jazz, you simply know it when you hear it.
Honestly, the only way to know what jazz is, is listen to it yourself.
As the great trumpet player Louis Armstrong said, If you gotta ask, you'll never
know. Question 2.
What does the man say about jazz music?
Question 3. What does the woman say about jazz?
Question 4. What should you do to appreciate different styles of jazz, according to
the woman? Conversation 2.
How did it go at the bank this morning?
Not well. My proposal was rejected.
Really? But why?
Bunch of reasons.
For starters, they said my credit history was not good enough.
Did they say how you could improve that?
Yes. They said that after five more years of paying my mortgage, then I would become
a more viable candidate for a business loan.
But right now, it's too risky for them to lend me money.
They fear I will default on any business loan I'm given.
Well, that doesn't sound fair.
Your business idea is amazing.
Did you show them your business plan?
What did they say?
They didn't really articulate any position regarding the actual business plan.
They simply looked at my credit history and determined it was not good enough.
They said the bank has strict guidelines and requirements as to who they can lend
money to. And I simply don't meet their financial threshold.
What if you asked for a smaller amount?
Maybe you could gather capital from other sources.
Smaller loans from more lenders?
You don't get it.
It doesn't matter the size of the loan I ask for or the type of business I propose.
That's all inconsequential.
The first thing every bank will do is study how much money I have and how much debt
I have before they decide whether or not to lend me any more money.
If I want to continue ahead with this dream of owning my own business, I have no
other choice but to build up my own finances.
I need around 20 more in personal savings and 50 less debt.
That's all there is to it.
I see now.
Well, it's a huge pity that they rejected your request, but don't lose hope.
I still think that your idea is great and that you would turn it into a phenomenal
success. Question 6.
Why was the woman's proposal rejected?
Question 7. What is the woman planning to do?
Question 8. What does the man suggest the woman do?
Section B. Directions.
this section you will hear two passages.
At the end of each passage you will hear three or four questions.
Both the passage and the questions will be spoken only once.
After you hear a you must choose the best answer from the four choices marked A, B,
C and D.
Then mark the corresponding letter on answer sheet 1 with a single line through the
centre. Passage 1.
There's a lot about Leo Sanchez and his farm in Salinas, California that seems
unusual. The national average farm size is around 440 acres, but his is only one
acre. The average age of farmers hovers around 58 years old, but he is just 26.
And Sanchez constantly attempts to improve everything from seeding techniques out in
the field to the promotion and sale of his produce online.
This is evidence of an experimental approach.
It's an approach not dictated by the confines of conventional, large -scale
agriculture led by international corporations.
While farming is often difficult for both the body and mind,
Sanchez says he and many of his fellow young farmers are motivated by desire to set
a new standard for agriculture.
Many of them are employing a multitude of technologies, some new and some not so
new. Recently, Sanchez bought a hand -operated tool which pulls out weeds and
loosens soil. It actually dates back to at least 1701.
It stands in sharp contrast to Sanchez's other gadget, a gas -powered flame weed
killer invented in 1997.
He simply doesn't discriminate when it comes to the newness of tools.
If it works, it works.
Farmers have a long history of invention and it's no different today.
Young farmers are guided by their love for agriculture and aided by their knowledge
of technology. To find inexpensive and appropriately sized tools, they collaborate
and innovate. Sometimes the old stuff just works better or more efficiently.
Question 10. What has motivated Leo Sanchez and his fellow young farmers to engage
in farming? Question 11.
Why did Leo Sanchez buy a hand -operated weeding tool?
Passage 2. Eat Grub is Britain's first new food company that breaks Western food
boundaries by introducing edible insects as a new source of food.
And Sainsbury's is the first UK supermarket to stock the company's crunchy roasted
crickets. Sainsbury's insists that such food is no joke and could be a new
sustainable source of protein.
Out of curiosity, I paid a visit to Sainsbury's.
As I put my hand into a packet of with their tiny eyes and legs,
the idea of one going in my mouth made me feel a little sick.
But the first bite was a pleasant surprise.
A little dry and lacking of taste, but at least a wing didn't get stuck in my
throat. The roasted seasoning largely overpowered any other flavour, although there
was a slightly bitter aftertaste.
The texture was crunchy, but smelled a little of cat food.
Eat Grub also recommends the crickets as a topping for noodles, soups and salads.
The company boasts that its dried crickets contain more protein than beef, chicken
and pork, as well as minerals like iron and calcium.
Unlike the production of bugs do not use up large amounts of water or feed, and
insect farming also produces far fewer greenhouse gases.
However, despite 2 billion people worldwide already supplementing their diet with
insects, consumer disgust remains a large barrier in many Western countries.
I'm not sure bugs will become a popular snack any time soon, but they're definitely
food for thought.
Question 13. What does the speaker say about his first bite of roasted crickets?
Question 14. What does Eat Grub say about his dried crickets?
Question 15. What does the passage say about insect farming?
Section C Directions In this section, you'll hear three recordings of lectures or
talks, followed by three or four questions.
The recordings will be played only once.
After you hear a question, you must choose the best answer from the four choices
marked A, B, C and D.
Then mark the corresponding letter on answer sheet 1 with a single line through the
centre. Recording 1 Have you ever had someone try to explain something to you a
dozen times with no luck?
But then when you see a picture, the idea finally clicks.
If that sounds familiar, maybe you might consider yourself a visual learner.
Or if reading or listening does the trick, maybe you feel like you're a verbal
learner. call these labels learning styles, but is there really a way to categorize
different types of students?
Well, it actually seems that multiple presentation formats, especially if one of
them is visual, help most people learn.
When psychologists and educators test for learning styles, they're trying to figure
out whether these are inherent traits that affect how well students learn, instead
of just a preference.
Usually, they start by giving a survey to figure out what style a student favours,
like visual or verbal learning.
Then they try to the students something with a specific presentation style, like
using visual aids, and do a follow -up test to see how much they learned.
That way, the researchers can see if the self -identified verbal learners really
learned better when the information was just spoken aloud, for example.
But according to a 2008 review, only one study that followed this design found that
students actually learned best with their preferred style.
But the study had some big flaws.
The researchers excluded two -thirds of the original participants because they
didn't seem to have any clear learning style from the survey at the beginning, and
they didn't even report the actual test scores in the final paper.
So, it doesn't really seem like learning styles are an inherent trait that we all
have. But that doesn't mean that all students will do amazingly if they just spend
all their time reading from a Instead, most people seem to learn better if they're
taught in several ways, especially if one is visual.
In one study, researchers tested whether students remembered lists of words better
if they heard them, saw them, or both.
And everyone seemed to do better if they got to see the words in print, even the
self -identified auditory learners.
Their preference didn't seem to matter.
Similar studies tested whether students learned basic physics and chemistry concepts
better by reading plain text or viewing pictures, too.
And everyone did better with the help of pictures.
Questions 16 to 18 are based on the recording you have just heard.
Question 16. Why do psychologists and educators study learning styles?
Question 17. What does the speaker say about one study mentioned in the 2008 review?
Question 18. What message does the speaker want to convey about learning at the end
of the talk?
Question What message does the speaker want to convey about learning at the end of
the Question 20.
What speaker want to convey about learning at the
Question 20. What message does the
Question 20. What message does the speaker want to convey about learning at the the
Question 20. What message
Question 20. What message does the speaker want to
Question 21. What message the speaker want to convey the Question 20.
What did leading economists predict 90 years ago?
Question 21. What is the result of denying workers right to make their own choices?
Today I'm going to talk about Germany's dream airport in Berlin.
The airport looks exactly like every other major modern airport in Europe, except
for one big problem.
More than seven years after it was originally supposed to open, it still stands
empty. Germany is known for its efficiency and refined engineering, but when it
comes to its new ghost airport, this reputation could not be further from the truth.
Plagued by long delays, perpetual mismanagement, and ever -soaring costs, the
airport has become something of a joke among Germans and a source of frustration for
local politicians, business leaders, and residents alike.
Planning for the new airport began in 1989.
At the time, it became clear that the newly reunified Berlin would need a modern
airport with far greater capacity than its existing airports.
The city broke ground on the new airport in 2006.
The first major sign of problems came in summer 2010, when the Construction
Corporation pushed the opening from October 2011 to June 2012.
In 2012, the city planned an opening ceremony, but less than a month beforehand,
inspectors found significant problems with the fire safety system and pushed the
opening back again to 2013.
wasn't just the smoke system, many other major problems subsequently emerged.
More than 90 meters of cable were incorrectly installed, 4,000 doors were wrongly
numbered, escalators were too short, and there was a shortage of check -in desks.
So why, with so many problems discovered, didn't the Airport Corporation decide to
give up on the project and start over?
The reason is simple.
People are often hesitant to terminate a project when they've already invested time
or resources into it, even if it might make logical sense to do so.
The longer the delays continued, the more problems inspectors found.
of the Planning Corporation has changed hands nearly as many times as the opening
date has been pushed back.
Initially, rather than appointing a general contractor to run the project,
the Corporation decided to manage it themselves, despite lack of experience with an
undertaking of that scale.
To compound the delays, unused airport is resulting in massive costs.
Every month it remains unopened, costs between 9 and 10 million euros.
Assuming all goes well, the airport should open in October 2020, but the still empty
airport stands as the biggest embarrassment to Germany's reputation for efficiency
and a continuing drain on city and state resources.
Question 23. Why was there a need for a new airport in Berlin?
Question 24. Why did Berlin postpone the opening of its Dream Airport again and
again? Question 25.
What happens while the airport remains unused?
This is end of listening comprehension.